Chapman's Reflexes,
Dr. John D.
Capobianco,
Department of OMM.
Session
objectives include
understanding the
neurophysiologic mechanism
of Chapman's
points, which
involve viscero
-traumatic reflexes.
Relate how Chapman's
reflexes connect
to the neuroendocrine
immune response.
Describe the common
manifestations
of endocrine
diseases as they
relate to
Chapman's reflexes.
Know that
Chapman's reflexes
involve the
sympathetic arm of
the autonomic
nervous system.
Use memory tools for
the vast array of
Chapman's reflexes,
such as the second
intercostal space and
lateral thigh or femur.
Incorporate Chapman's
reflexes into the
five models of
osteopathic medicine. Dr.
Frank Chapman
was a student
of Dr. Andrew
Taylor Still.
His concept of
diagnosing autonomic tone
by the fill of the
tissues recognized the
unlimited potential
of the lymphatics.
Dr. Chapman practiced
and charted his
lymphatic reflexes
for nearly 30 years.
Upon his death, his
wife, Dr. Ada Hinckley
Chaplin, and his
brother-in-law, Dr.
Charles Owens, along
with Dr. W. F. Link,
assembled his writings
into a book entitled
An Endocrine
Interpretation of Chapman's
Reflexes. This set
the stage for the
concept of the unity
of hormones, immunity,
and the autonomic
nervous system, in
particular the sympathetic
nervous system.
Chapman's reflexes
have also been called
the receptive organ.
These are tissue texture
changes both anteriorly
usually in the
intercostal fascia or
in the periosteum of the
rib and posteriorly
along the spinal
vertebral musculature
in particular the short
and long restrictors
of the spine i'm going
to quote dr h.r small
who is a student at
the chicago college of
osteopathy in regards
to the anatomy of the
chapman's reflex and
i quote the intercostal
nerve carries
fibers of or is connected
with the sympathetic
nervous system. A
typical spinal nerve is
made up of fibers from
the posterior root
of the cord and its
ganglion together with
the anterior root. In
the spinal cord, there
are connected fibers
which synapse with
the two roots outside
the cord. These two
fibers emerge through
the vertebra by way of
the intervertebral
foramen. The anterior
and posterior roots
are unsheathed in the
same sheath and immediately
begin to branch.
The spinal nerve
branches into a posterior
and anterior primary
division. The
posterior primary
division further branches
into a lateral and
medial cutaneous
branch which innervates
the skin on either
side of the spine
for about six inches
while the posterior
primary division
also innervates the
longitudinal muscles
of the back. The
anterior primary
division continues
around the thorax as
the intercostal nerve
it communicates with
the sympathetic
ganglion which is
located on the anterior
lateral side of
the bodies of the
vertebra in the thorax
the intercostal branch
continues in the
groove on the anterior
inferior border of
the rib and gives off
a lateral cutaneous
branch which innervates
the skin in this
region of the thorax
as far as the sternum
the intercostal
nerve innervates the
external internal
intercostal muscles and
with its sympathetic
fibers the intercostal
arteries, veins,
lymphatic nodes, etc.
In the intercostal
space between the
anterior and posterior
layers of the anterior
intercostal fascia
is located some
lymphoid tissue. It
is within this tissue
that a Chapman's
reflex will be found.
It is important to
realize that Chapman's
reflexes are at its
very core viscerosomatic
reflexes. This is
an illustration
of a organ which is
irritated on the lower
right hand side of
this image. It sends
signals into the
dorsal horn of the
spinal cord. Here
there is cross-synaptic
noise with somatic nerves
that will innervate
muscle both anteriorly
and posteriorly.
This is called a
visceral somatic
reflex. When you treat
a Chapman's reflex,
you inhibit the
muscle and fascial
tension, and this
will reflexively
inhibit any input
or excessive gain
input into the
affected organ system.
These are also
called ganglia form
contractions. These
are areas of hyper
congestion from
hypersympathetic tone to
the deep intercostal
fascia, particularly
anteriorly, which
result in lymphatic
edema and mild
fascial thickening.
This is reflected
as a painful
nodule that, as
Patricorn described,
was small, smooth,
firm, discreetly
palpable, and
approximately two to
three millimeters
in diameter. It may
also increase the
size of an almond.
Note that posterior
points may feel like
any particular somatic
dysfunction but
have been described
as quote stringy.
Ganglia form
contraction that blocks
lymphatic drainage
causes inflammation
in tissues distal
to the blockage.
This lies deep
to the skin lying
on the deep fascia
or periosteum.
Typically paired
reflexes are on the
back and front of
the body and they are
fixed at specific
anatomic locations
which tend to relate
to the sympathetic
innervation of that
particular organ.
This particular
slide illustrates the
connectivity of the
lymphatic to the connective
tissue of the body, and
this further illustrates
the effect of motion
upon lymphatics.
This slide represents the
anterior
Chapman's points.
This slide represents
posterior
Chapman's points.
There are areas of
high-density Chapman's
reflexes. One in
particular is the
second intercostal
space. This includes the
bronchus, esophagus,
thyroid, and heart,
and we like to call
this mnemonic BETH.
The clinical correlations
would include
a patient who has
bronchitis, who has
also status post
-myocardial infarction
with a history of
gastroesophageal reflux
disease, and
Hashimoto's thyroiditis.
There are other
areas of high-density
Chapman's reflexes,
and this includes
the lateral femur.
There are basically
four structures that
make up Chapman's
reflexes in the
outer thigh and they
include the broad
ligament, the prostate,
the colon. Understand
that the ascending
colon would be on the
right thigh and the
descending colon would
be on the left thigh.
Also sciatic neuritis,
which is also
called lumbosacral
radiculopathy is also on
the outer thigh
we like to use the
memory tool back pain
causes spasm for bpcs
the osteopathic
importance includes the
treatment of these
reflexes altering
sympathetic influences
on any related organ
and therefore
disease As a result,
this affects the
visceral somatic reflex.
Diagnostic importance
as a result
of predictable and
consistent reflexes
may relate to
diseased organs.
It is important to realize
before encountering
any type of
lymphatic treatment,
the thoracic inlet
slash outlet in T1 to T6
should be treated.
Once they are treated
and the practitioner
wants to endeavor
Chapman's reflexes,
one must first treat
the pelvis, and this
includes anonymous.
Next, treat the
anterior points with one
finger pad applied
directly on the gangliform
contraction. Apply a
rotatory force anywhere
from 10 seconds to 2
minutes. This could
actually vary from 2
seconds to 10 minutes.
This is a general
guideline. Basically,
treat till you feel
the nodule resolving,
there's a softening
of the tissues, and
there's a marked decrease
or absence of pain.
Next, treat the posterior
reflexes if necessary.
Understand the importance
of the pelvis. The
sympathetic nervous
system terminates just
anterior to the sacral
coccyx-yield joint.
When treating the
pelvis, one may
utilize the inguinal
ligament, also
called Poupart's
ligament, to diagnose
anonimate or
pelvic dysfunction.
This slide illustrates
a simple muscle
energy slash direct
myofascial technique to
correct an anonimate
pelvic dysfunction.
Understand that
Chapman's reflexes are
a subset of
viscerosomatic sympathetic
reflexes. This
particular research
demonstrated a
viscerosomatic reflex of
the adrenal gland,
which is T10 to T11.
The actual Chapman's
reflex is T11 to
T12 posteriorly.
In this particular
instance, systolic
and diastolic blood
pressure was lowered
by 15 to eight
millimeters of
mercury respectively.
This overall treatment
decreased the
sympathetic input into
the adrenal gland which
lowered the serum
aldosterone levels.
This slide illustrates
a Chapman's
reflex of the adrenal
gland. Notice that
the actual reflex
is marked by the
X which tends to be
between the spinous
process of the
level above to the
transverse process
of the level below.
There could also be
reflexes between each
transverse process.
In general, these
particular points
lie along the short
restrictors of the spine
and long restrictors
of the spine. It
is only important
to understand that
these points are
generally in the same
location, whether you
are talking about the
spinous, transverse,
or transverse
-transverse processes.
There has been peer
-reviewed research.
Chapman's reflexes
in the hospitalized
patient with
pneumonia included a
statistical significance
for the presence
of Chapman's
reflexes in the third
and fourth intercostal
space and between
T3 and T4 and T4
and T5 posteriorly.
This slide
illustrates a 19
-year-old African
-American female
who had nephrotic
syndrome.
Part of her overall
osteopathic treatment
included Chapman's
reflexes. The
patient avoided
toxicity of chemotherapy
by applying osteopathic
manipulation,
and she
subsequently avoided
between 1,500
and 2,700 cc's of
urine within a
couple of days.
The patient was
discharged on day eight.
Dr. Irwin Kor
was a leader
in osteopathic research.
His simple statement
was, in every disease
process, there is
hypersympathetic
activity, and sustained
sympathetic activity
is a common factor in
disease. understand
that hypersympathetic
activity to the
lymphatics creates
constriction and thusly
congestion and this
is part of the overall
lymphatic myofascial
tender point that one
finds with a Chapman's
reflex this slide
illustrates the overall
schematic of the
sympathetic nervous
system to the organs
There are several upper
respiratory Chapman's
reflexes, which include
the pharynx, tonsils,
larynx, and nasal
sinuses. Note that the
ear is on the medial
edge of the clavicle.
Chapman's reflexes
for otitis
media, as previously
discussed,
is at the medial clavicle
anteriorly and
posteriorly along
the transverse
process of C1.
In the case of
sinusitis, Chapman's
reflexes anteriorly are
on the upper edge of
the second rib and
first intercostal space
anteriorly, and
at C2 between the
spinous and transverse
process posteriorly.
Chapman's reflexes
for the thyroid
include the second
intercostal space
as previously
discussed the bronchus
esophagus thyroid
and heart are
all at the second
intercostal space
posteriorly the
thyroid is along
the transverse
process of t2 know
that the cardiopulmonary
points include
the second
third and fourth
intercostal space
representing the heart
upper lung and lower
lung respectively
as previously noted
for the esophagus which
can include the clinical
syndrome of GERD
includes the second
intercostal space anteriorly
and a t2 between
the spinous and
transverse process
posteriorly there are several
upper gastrointestinal
Chapman's reflexes
it is important to
note that there are two
liver reflexes one at
the fifth intercostal
space on the right
and one at the sixth
intercostal space on
the right there are also
two stomach Chapman's
reflexes one for acidity
at the left fifth
intercostal space and
one for peristalsis at
the left sixth intercostal
space also note
that there is a
gallbladder reflex along
the anterior medial aspect
of the right radial
head approximately.
Further, note that there
is a splenic reflex
along the anterior
medial radial head
approximately on the left
side of the body. There
are several posterior
points noted here.
In a patient with
Crohn's, for example, who
has inflammation of
a small intestine,
there could be Chapman's
reflexes along the
8th, 9th, and 10th
intercostal space
anteriorly and between
the intertransverse
processes of eight through
eleven posteriorly.
In cases of infection
there is a splenic
Chapman's reflex noted
at the left seventh
intercostal space
anteriorly and between the
transverse processes of
T7 and T8 on the left.
Chapman's reflex for
the appendix is a
very common entity for
the national boards.
It is also very important
for the diagnosis
of your surgical
patient. Please note
that the right tip
of the 12th rib
represents an anterior
point for appendicitis
and posteriorly
along the right into
transverse space. Also
note that anteriorly
along the umbilicus
at 7 o'clock, there
is a Chapman's reflex
for appendicitis.
For the lower
gastrointestinal Chapman's
reflex, one needs
to simply flip
the intestines down
over the thighs.
As previously
noted, the outer
thigh represents
the colon.
Here you can see the
upper outer thigh
on the right represents
the cecum, the
ascending colon would
be along the middle
of the outer femur,
and the hepatic flexure
in the beginning
of the transverse
colon would be just
above the right knee.
On the left side,
the sigmoid colon
would be along the
upper outer aspect of
the left femur, the
descending colon
would be along the
middle outer thigh,
and the splenic flexure
and the remainder
of the transverse
colon would be along
the distal aspect
of the left femur.
There are several
******* urinary points.
I also included
the adrenal tender
point here, which is
lateral and superior
to the umbilicus.
No kidney, bladder,
ovaries, and
******. There are no
specific testicular
Chapman's reflexes.
One will use the
ovarian tender
point on the upper
aspect of the medial
portion of the
***** tubercle.
The broad ligament
and prostate are again
on the outer thigh and
the uterus is noted
to be along the obturator
foramen anteriorly.
The overall sympathetic
input into the
******* urinary system
is T10 to L2. Note
that the ****** tend
to be derived from T10
to T11, but yet the
genitalia tends to be
innervated sympathetically
from T12 to L2.
Note, in contrast
to the ovarian
Chapman's reflex, which
is on the superior
medial aspect of
the ***** tubercle,
the urethra is
in the inner edge
of the *****
ramus near the
upper edge of the
***** symphysis.
Posteriorly,
the Chapman's
reflex for the
urethra is along
the transverse
process of L2.
There are Chapman's
reflexes for the
extremities as well,
in particular the upper
extremity. In any case
of shoulder, elbow,
or hand, in particular
dupetrin's contracture
of the upper extremity
there is something
called the parkas
reflex which is on
the upper outer
anterior aspect of the
scapula this is along
the pseudogangling of
the teres minor muscle
posteriorly between
the transverse process
of t3 and t4 can
be found reflexes for
the upper extremity
as well in addition
there are third rib
dysfunctions anteriorly
which have been
associated with upper
extremity dysfunction.
This slide illustrates
Parker's reflex.
Again this particular
reflex is noted with
DuPietre's contracture
or any type of
sympathetic activity
or hyperactivity of the
upper extremity including
frozen shoulder.
This slide represents
the pseudoganglion
associated with the
teres minor muscle
that is very tender
in Parker's reflex.
An endocrine
interpretation of Chapman's
reflexes stresses
the importance of the
neuroendocrine immune
system. An example of this
particular PTAS syndrome
would be the response
of thyrotropin and
thyroxine hormones, which
stimulate natural killer
cells or NK cells,
and also produces T
-cells, respectively.
Stress, or the
musculoskeletal ready
state, is mediated
by the sympathetic
nervous system
and promotes the
release of cortisol
from the adrenal
glands, which also
modulate immunocytes.
However, increased
hypersympathetic
tone to the adrenal
gland could actually
depress the overall
immune system
through too much
production of cortisol.
As previously discussed,
when one endeavors
to treat the
lymphatic system, that
the thoracic inlet
slash outlet and T1 to
T6 should be treated.
However, before
specific Chapman's
reflexes are utilized,
one must correct
anonymous
dysfunction as
previously noted.